This week I am going to make Alton
Brown's serious vanilla ice cream. We'll
break it down into numbers and see if
it's any good.
[Music]
So last week the breast milk ice cream,
it didn't do too bad considering how
controversial it actually was, but you
know, it's nice to do something
different sometimes. But today's video
is Alton Brown's serious vanilla ice
cream. Um I'm going to make it exactly
as the recipe online says.
We're going to look at the result and
see if we can improve it in any way,
shape, or form. What we've got here,
according to the recipe, and I will put
a picture on screen of the recipe that
we're working from, 150 g of sugar
separated into 100 g and 50 g. 60 g of
water, 15 g of liquid pectin, 480 g of
half and half, which is 10% fat for
those people outside North America. 245
gram of heavy cream, which is 34 to 36%
fat, depending on where in North America
you are. And 40 gram of vanilla bean
paste. And finally, it's 0.1 teaspoon of
salt. So, a pinch of salt. And this is
I'm using sea salt. Don't use table
salt. It's got other stuff in it as
well. So, for those in Europe, etc., You
can you make 10% fat cream by using
something like single cream and just
topping it up with water. So we just
need to reduce that fat down a little
bit as and you can do the same for the
cream in this recipe. So this uses the
heavy cream 34 36%. If you're using like
double cream which is 50% then just add
water to bring it up to 36% fat and then
decount off how much you need. To be
fair, I've looked at the numbers already
for this recipe and I think it could
probably do with a little bit of
adjustment anyway. So, we'll talk about
that later. So, according to the
directions, we have to take our 50 g of
sugar, which is this, in a small
saucepan with our 60 g of water, and get
that to a boil. So, let's do that. Once
that sugar water comes to a boil, we
need to add our 15 g of pectin and then
bring it back to a rolling boil for 1
minute and then remove it from the heat.
So, I'm going to do that and then I'll
come back. Right, we're up to a boil.
We're going to add in our 15 g of liquid
pectin.
Get it back on the heat.
And it says we need to boil that for 1
minute. So,
let's do that. Right, there is our 1
minute. It says exactly 1 minute. That's
really precise. Remove from heat and
leave a room temperature to cool for 25
minutes. So, let's just leave that
there. 25 minutes time. Look, it's/4 to
10, give or take 1 minute. So, 10
temperature should it says temperature
should land about 89 Fahrenheit. So,
let's make sure we do everything
correctly. I need to change to
Fahrenheit. There we go. Fahrenheit.
What are we at now?
We're 167 Fahrenheit. So, we got a ways
to come down yet. So the next stage
while the pectin while the pectin
mixture cools combine the remaining half
a cup of sugar with the half and half
with our half and half and our cream
which is here. Make sure we get all of
this stuff out. One tablespoon which
says 20 g. I'm not sure that's right but
I know that is pretty much 15 g. So I'm
going to add that remaining 5 g in like
that. Just make sure that all goes in
there. And the salt, I mean, it's 0.1
teaspoon. So,
like that. Not a lot of salt going into
this. And it says we need to heat it up
to 185F and then remove it and steep it
for 20 minutes. So, that will tie in
with this. So, let's get this on heat.
So, we've got our pect in here. I'm just
swirling this around gently cuz it will
stick to the sides. it will create like
a sticky
gloopy layer on the outside edge of your
saucepan if you don't do this. So, just
agitate it for, you know, a few times
during this cooling phase. Let's clear
up. And once this is up to 185 F, we'll
get it on here. There we go.
185F. Off the heat it comes. Says to
cover and steep for 20 minutes. I don't
have a lid for this saucepan. So, we're
gonna
we're going to cover it with foil.
Obviously, we're covering a really hot
liquid, so that's going to condensate on
the underside of this or lid as well.
So, when you remove it, try not to drip
all that water back in to the mixture.
So, 20 minutes. This you got about 15
minutes to wait. So, I'll come back when
that time has passed. All right. All
right. So, our pectin needs to be down
to what did he say? 89 Fahrenheit. 84.
We've got our bowl here for storing.
Let's get this out. Lots of water.
Try to keep that out of the way there.
So, let's get a little whisk. It says to
thoroughly stir our pectin mixture. So,
let's stir that. And our pectin mixture
is going into our dairy mixture. Stir
this up.
And then we need to add in our remaining
20 g
of
vanilla bean paste. We need to cool it
down to room temperature using an ice
bath. Ice bath in. This goes.
And we're going to stir this now until
this comes down to room temperature. So
I'm going to keep stirring this until we
come down to room temperature. Really
didn't take very long. So, let's get it
out of there. Get rid of this. Transfer.
It says transfer to an airtight
container and chill in the fridge for
six to 24 hours. So, it's quite a broad
time scale, but essentially what we're
what we're trying to do is just bring
this down to fridge temperature, and
that additional time will allow that
vanilla flavor to mature. So, that in
mind, in the fridge that goes. And I'll
do a full 24 hours, give or take. So,
we'll come back tomorrow morning and
churn this puppy up. So, the recipe says
to split the sugar for the pectin with
the water, heat the dairy to 185F, then
steep for 20 minutes, and then again for
6 to 24 hours. Now, in reality, the
initial sugar is only there to activate
the pectin, and the water is just there
to stop it burning. The 185F dairy
heating just dissolves the fats and sets
the pace. The pectin integration and the
20-minut steep totally useless. The
overnight chill does all of this work.
Still, the recipe is missing something
big to be truly serious though. Also, by
denaturing the proteins by heating up to
185, that's just not enough to give this
ice cream the texture and mouth feel
that it really deserves with a name like
it's got. Okay. Alton Brown's
serious vanilla ice cream. Uh,
relatively easy to make. Um, a couple of
things I'd do different, but smells
good.
Oh, cold.
It's got a great taste. There's no twist
about it. Just one thing. It's lacking
so many solids. It's down in the 31 to
32% solids, which is why it's so cold.
You know what it's like when you you
take some ice cream and you put it in
your mouth. it. When you compare one
version of ice cream to another, one is
really cold and one is, you know, normal
ice cream, the one that is really cold
is always low in solids. And that's what
we got here. It It's almost 10% too low
in solids. And for those people that
have been here long enough, the one
ingredient that is missing from this
recipe is skim milk powder or low-fat
milk powder or zero fat milk powder,
whatever it's called where you're from.
That is the thing missing from this.
It's a delicious ice cream. Really nice.
Uses pectin.
It's an unusual stabilizer for ice
cream, but it's decent.
But it needs those extra solids from
somewhere. It has a minus 10 centrade
serving temperature, which is for me
personally, you know, a little bit high,
which means it's got to come out of the
freezer for, you know, five or 10
minutes to warm up before you can scoop
it. So you that would be resolved with
that skim milk powder as well. The
lactose in the milk powder would help
bring that serving temperature back
around to where we want it to be. But
it's a good ice cream. Absolutely.
For those people that have never made
it, give it a bash and let me know what
you think in the comments. Thanks very
much for watching. Don't forget to like
and subscribe. Next week I'm going to do
a Ben & Jerry's remake cuz I haven't
done one of those in a while. So stick
around and I'll see you then.